{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This system was allegedly exploited when Justinian successfully sent spies disguised as Christian monks to steal eggs. Thanks to the missions of Zhang Qian, this system was greatly expanded. Stops known as caravanserais helped service this system. Glassware and gold coins honoring Antoninus Pius were exchanged for textiles along this route, which connected Europe with Asia. For ten points, identify this Chinese trade route cultivated by the Han dynasty.",
      "answer": "Silk Road"
    },
    {
      "question": "The end of this battle was negotiated at the Moore House under the direction of John Laurens. Charles O’Hara, after being rebuked by two others, gave Benjamin Lincoln his sword at the end of this battle. In the days following this battle, Thomas Graves rescued American Loyalists who had escaped from this battle but was forced to flee rather than face the French fleet. A British band legendarily played “The World Turn’d Upside Down” at, for ten points, what 1781 battle, the last major battle of the American Revolution?",
      "answer": "Siege of Yorktown"
    },
    {
      "question": "The death of this empire’s founding ruler Digha Ciss´e caused a power struggle between his sons Khine and Dyabe; when Dyabe lost, he legendarily sacrificed a virgin to the snake Bida every year until he died. Al-Bakri wrote of dogs with golden collars in this empire, whose original Soninke name was Wagadou. Controlling the salt and gold trade across the Sahara, this empire was later absorbed by Mali. For ten points, the Gold Coast is presently named for what medieval West African empire?",
      "answer": "Ghana or Wagadou before mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city feuded with the Ercole d’Este [AIR-co-lay DES-tay] to protect its salt-mining rights in the Commachio in the Ferrara War. This city guarded one aspect of its trade by preventing its glassmakers from leaving Murano. This city’s conquest of Dalmatia was celebrated by this city every Ascension Day, where the ship Bucentaur would go out to sea and a ring would be dropped into the water. The Marriage of the Sea ritual took place in, for ten points, what Italian “serene republic” that was led by a doge?",
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these laws which was applied after death was known as mortmain, or “the dead hand.” Enforcing these laws during the ancien r´egime was outsourced to the paramilitary General Farm. The octroi was one of these laws applied when entering cities, and the corv´ee was one regarding manual labor. Inconsistent application of one of these laws, the gabelle, resulted in a salt smuggling crisis. The vingti´eme and taille were sales and land types of, for ten points, what monetary levy?",
      "answer": "taxes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Robert Landsburg died taking photographs of this event and, in his last moments, laid on top of his backpack to protect its contents. For ten points, name this 1980 in which a volcano in Washington erupted. David Johnston radioed “Vancouver! Vancouver! This is it!” before dying during this event despite being over six miles away. The destruction of camps around Spirit Lake as part of this event resulted in the death of Harry R. Truman. For ten points, name this 1980 event in which the eruption of a Washington volcano decimated the surrounding area.",
      "answer": "the eruption of Mount St. Helens"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jules Michelet gave the first definition of this period in his History of France. Jakob Burkhardt argued that this period gave birth to modern individuality in The Civilization of [this period]. This period’s reputation for cultural advancement has been challenged by historians who emphasize its nostalgia for classicism and continuity with the Middle Ages. For ten points, name this era usually characterized by the flourishing of art and humanism in 15th and 16th century Italy.",
      "answer": "The Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "question": "Under this man’s Personalist government, members of the ruling Can Lao party were originally told to keep their memberships secret. This leader reorganized 14,000 villages into “strategic hamlets” in order to secure backing from the countryside. This leader’s unpopularity grew after launching a series of raids on the Xa Loi Pagoda. His downfall was precipitated by the self-immolation of Buddhist monk Thich Quang Duc. For ten points, identify this American-backed president of South Vietnam.",
      "answer": "Ngo Dinh Diem"
    },
    {
      "question": "A parable from this work titled “The Eldest Lady’s Tale” is likely an early Cinderella story. A caliph finds a dead body in a chest in a section of this work titled “The Three Apples.” In this work, the slave-girl Morgiana saves her master by pouring boiling oil on thieves hidden in jars. Stories in this collection feature historical figures like Khosrow II and Harun al-Rashid. For ten points, name this collection of stories that features the characters Sinbad the Sailor and Ali Baba.",
      "answer": [
        "Arabian Nights",
        "One Thousand and One Nights"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, William Fishback helped pass an amendment that banned payment of Holford Bonds. A political family in this state formed after Robert Crittenden broke dueling etiquette. The Conway-Johnson family operated in this state where Joseph Brooks and Elisha Baxter started a “war” for the governorship. The refusal of Orval Faubus to allow integrated schools in this state led Dwight Eisenhower to send in the national guard. For ten points, name this state where, in 1957, nine black students were enrolled in Little Rock Central High School.",
      "answer": "Arkansas"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A pectoral found in this place with a red disk and a blue beetle represents the prenomen of one person in this place, which was discovered when a water boy stumbled on a stone. This place’s treasury contained a gold-covered canopic chest and the remains of two stillborn children. One object found in this place has quartz and obsidian eyes and an elongated gold and lapis lazuli beard. That mask was found in, for ten points, what tomb, officially named KV62, discovered by Howard Carter in the Valley of Kings?",
        "answer": [
          "The Tomb of Tutenkhamun",
          "KV62 before mention"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Damaged cartouches in Tutankhamun’s tomb indicate that his successor Horemheb attempted to do this to Tutankhamun. Hatshepshut was also a victim of this process, which caused her namesake “Problem.”",
        "answer": [
          "being erased from history",
          "damnatio memoriae,",
          "obvious equivalents"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. One of these two countries implemented Operation Streamline to control illegal immigrants from the other during the early-2000s. The Chamizal dispute clarified the border between these two countries, which is the most commonly crossed border in the world. Yuma and Nogales were added to one country after the Gadsden Purchase modified these two countries’ border. For ten points, name these two countries in the Western Hemisphere whose planned border wall has been a source of controversy since 2016.",
        "answer": "United States and Mexico"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician’s February 2019 calls to remove sections of the border wall in El Paso provoked President Trump to call it the “end of his political career.” This man, who lost the 2018 Senate election to Ted Cruz, road-tripped across the American Southwest before announcing his presidential candidacy in March.",
        "answer": [
          "Beto O’Rourke",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The pagan god Baal became known as Belos, which was later translated as the name of this Greek deity. Israel targeted Iran with a cyber-attack project named after “Nitro” and this deity. The continent of Europe was named after a lady who was kidnapped by this deity. For ten points, name this son of Rhea and Cronus, known as Jupiter to the Romans, who became the king of the Greek gods and wielder of lightning bolts.",
        "answer": "Zeus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Europa was kidnapped by Zeus in the shape of this animal. Io was forced to wander until she met Prometheus at a strait afterwards partially named for this animal, the Bosphorus.",
        "answer": [
          "cow",
          "equivalents like bull",
          "heifer"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Much of this present-day state was explored by Gaspar de Portola who expelled its Jesuits in 1767. Francis Drake landed in this modern-day state during his circumnavigation, claiming it as New Albion for the English. Juan Cabrillo was the first European to navigate the coast of this modern state, whose Baja and Alta sub-regions are divided between Mexico and the United States. For ten points, name this West Coast state where Spanish missions evolved into cities like San Francisco.",
        "answer": "California BONUS:Thisman’snamesake“Fort”wouldlaterdevelopintoSacramento.Hisemployee,JamesMarshall, discovered gold in California at his namesake “Mill”. ANSWER: John Sutter 5 This house originated after Ren´e of Chalon died in battle, leaving another ruler to add the title of a French principality to this house. A military strategist from this house won the Battle of Turnhout and was named Maurice. Members of this family did not rule during the First Stadtholderless Period. Wilhelmina from this house technically was the last of its male line and became a symbol of the resistance during WWII. For ten points, name this royal house which names the current Dutch ruling family. ANSWER: House of Orange-Nassau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Grand Pensionary led the Dutch Republic during the first Stadholderless Period, though he and his brother were lynched after the “disaster year.”",
        "answer": [
          "Jan",
          "Johan de Witt"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s president Jose Ramos Horta was critically injured in a 2008 assassination attempt. This country’s former Prime Minister Mari Alkatiri was forced to resign following accusations that he had hired a hit squad. Xanana Gusmao was the first president of this country, where the Fretilin party fought against Indonesian occupiers.The Santa Cruz massacre occurred in this country’s capital of Dili. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country which gained its independence in 2002.",
        "answer": "Timor Leste or East Timor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2011, Timor Leste applied to join this regional organisation which was founded in 1967 with the Bangkok Declaration.",
        "answer": "ASEAN or Association of Southeast Asian Nations"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Simon Sterne questioned this company’s leadership as part of the Hepburn Committee. John Dustin Archbold served as the primary spokesman for this company in which role he survived a 1915 assassination attempt by the IWW. This company is the subject of a work whose final chapter, “The Compromise of 1889”, explores how it silenced organized opposition and individual complaint. Ida Tarbell wrote a history of this company exposing their lie about supporting independent pipelines. John D. Rockefeller founded, for ten points, what often corrupt oil company?",
        "answer": "Standard Oil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ida Tarbell’s muckraking The History of the Standard Oil Company was published serially in this magazine.",
        "answer": "McClure’s"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While departing Sicily, this leader said “What a wrestling ground we are leaving, my friends, for the Carthaginians and the Romans.” This enemy of Antigonus II Gonatas died after being hit in the head by a tile thrown by an old woman in Argos. This ally of Tarentum used elephants to win the Battle of Heraclea and his forces were later weakened despite winning the Battle of Asculum. Victories with unsustainably heavy costs to the victor are named after, for ten points, what Epirote general?",
        "answer": "Pyrrhus of Epirus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pyrrhic War was fought in an area of southern Italy given what name, which refers to the Hellenic colonists who established cities like Tarentum and Neapolis?",
        "answer": "Magna Graecia"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "War of 1812",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Baltimore fort where Francis Scott Key was inspired to compose the words for “The Star Spangled Banner.”",
          "answer": "Fort McHenry"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Lady who saved the Lansdowne portrait during the burning of DC.",
          "answer": [
            "Dolley Payne Todd Madison",
            "any underlined name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1813 naval battle in a Great Lake’s Put-in-Bay where Oliver Hazard Perry fought from the Lawrence and Niagara.",
          "answer": "Battle of Lake Erie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scout who was ambushed and wounded at Lundy’s Lane and later developed the Anaconda Plan in the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Winfield Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "August 24, 1814 battle in Maryland that immediately preceded the burning of DC.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bladensburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "1817 treaty, well after the war, that demilitarized the Great Lakes.",
          "answer": "Rush-Bagot Treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Major General who led the siege of Detroit in August 1812.",
          "answer": "Isaac Brock"
        },
        {
          "question": "American general and governor of Michigan who was court-martialed for surrendering Detroit to the British.",
          "answer": "William Hull"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battles of the Napoleonic Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nation that won many of them under Napoleon’s leadership.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive 1805 naval victory in which Horatio Nelson destroyed a combined Napoleonic/Spanish fleet.",
          "answer": "Battle of Trafalgar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive 1805 victory that ended the War of the Third Coalition, often nicknamed the Battle of the Three Emperors.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Austerlitz",
            "Battle of Three Emperors if given early"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "September 1812 battle where Napoleon held back the Imperial Guard while capturing Moscow.",
          "answer": "Battle of Borodino"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation that lost the Battle of Jena-Auerstedt [yay-nuh our-staht] in the War of the Fourth Coalition.",
          "answer": "Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Iron Marshal” who defeated the main enemy army at Jena-Auerstedt.",
          "answer": "Marshal Louis-Nicolas Davout"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian commander who defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Aspern Essling before losing the Battle of Wagram.",
          "answer": [
            "Archduke Charles Laurentius, Duke of Teschen",
            "either",
            "both names",
            "Karl in place of Charles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle at the end of the War of the Fourth Coalition in which Bennigsen’s forces were decisively defeated by Napoleon and Jean Lanes.",
          "answer": "Battle of Friedland"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Tiananmen Square",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chinese city where the square is located.",
          "answer": "Beijing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which anti-government protests broke out in the square. The Berlin Wall opened in this year.",
          "answer": "1989"
        },
        {
          "question": "Date on which the square was cleared by military force. Give either the real date or the alternate date used online to avoid censorship.",
          "answer": [
            "June 4th or May 35th",
            "year not needed, but don’t",
            "answers that give you the wrong year"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Military vehicles that were briefly stopped by an unidentified man the following day.",
          "answer": [
            "Type 59 tanks",
            "Tank Man"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2010 Nobel Peace Prize laureate who was among the student protesters.",
          "answer": "Liu Xiaobo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Torch-bearing statue built of papier-mache and foam during the protests and destroyed in the clearing.",
          "answer": [
            "Goddess of Democracy and Freedom",
            "any combination of Spirit/Goddess of Freedom/Liberty/Democracy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Communist general secretary whose death inspired the inital march to Tiananmen.",
          "answer": "Hu Yaobang"
        },
        {
          "question": "Premier who ordered martial law during the protests.",
          "answer": "Li Peng"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An opera by this composer features arias from two unhappily married couples sung during a game of bridge. This composer set 10 old Irish poems in his Hermit Songs. This composer’s (20 pts)",
        "Capricorn Concerto is named for a house he lived in with his partner Gian Carlo Menotti. This composer set a text by James Agee in his (10 pts)",
        "Knoxville: Summer of 1915. This composer’s own adaptation of the second movement of his string quartet, also set as a choral Agnus Dei, was broadcast over the radio after FDR’s death. For ten points, name this composer of Adagio for Strings."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel Barber"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Agent A-54 was a double agent in the Abwehr for this nation. A leader of this nation published “Racial Problems in Hungary” and fought Jewish blood libels in the Hilsner Case. (20 pts)",
        "Emil Hacha led this country as a Protectorate. The “Fourth Plan” was proposed by this country’s leader Edvard (10 pts)",
        "Benes, who passed decrees to expel ethnic Germans. This country’s defenses were crippled after Britain and France forced it to give Sudetenland to Nazi Germany. The Munich Agreement targeted, for ten points, what no longer extant country that was governed from Prague?"
      ],
      "answer": "Czechoslovakia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man served as Mormaer of Moray and defeated his predecessor in his highest position at Bothnagowan before himself being killed at Lumphanan. This man’s reign was chronicled by John of Fordun, but the most famous account of this person is based on (20 pts)",
        "Holinshed’s Chronicles. In that account, he is told he can’t be killed by anyone born of a woman’s womb by (10 pts)",
        "three witches, only to fall to the Thane of Fife, who was born by Caesarian section. Malcolm III succeeded, for ten points, what Scottish king whose actual reign was more successful than depicted in a namesake Shakespeare tragedy?"
      ],
      "answer": "Macbeth"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 1980 Boston Globe article about this man had the accidental, but humorous, headline “Mush from the Wimp.” The Washington Post created a political cartoon parodying Jaws, creatively named PAWS, to mock this man after he was “attacked” by a (20 pts)",
        "swamp rabbit. This man challenged the notion that “There is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe” in a debate with (10 pts)",
        "Gerald Ford. This President ordered the disastrous Operation Eagle Claw, a failed attempt to end the Iran-Hostage Crisis. For ten points, name this oft-mocked President who only served one term after being elected in 1976."
      ],
      "answer": "Jimmy Carter"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An event at this venue is the subject of Shut Up and Play the Hits!, a documentary about LCD Soundsystem’s last concert before their 2011 hiatus. In 1971, Ravi Shankar joined George Harrison and many performers at this venue for two benefit performances in the Concert for (20 pts)",
        "Bangladesh. The 1924 Klanbake took place in this venue, which some people want to move to allow the renovation of (10 pts)",
        "Penn Station. For ten points, name this Manhattan arena that hosted Billy Joel, is the home of the NBA’s Knicks, and hosts numerous New York City events."
      ],
      "answer": "Madison Square Garden or MSG"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One regiment from this country was annihilated during an offensive at Beaumont-Hamel. A memorial designed by Walter Seymond Allwell stands on Hill 145, which was taken by an assault by this country’s forces in a battle sometimes called “The Birth of” this nation at (20 pts)",
        "Vimy Ridge. The Third Battle of Ypres was ended when Arthur Currie led forces from this country to capture (10 pts)",
        "Passchendaele. In a 1917 Conscription Crisis, this country’s French speakers opposed the Military Service Act and the British war effort. For ten points, name this former Dominion in North America."
      ],
      "answer": "Dominion of Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Treaty of Hartford ended a border dispute between this man and Theophilus Eaton. This man survived a leg amputation during an attack on Saint Martin. During this man’s absence, the town of (20 pts)",
        "Pavonia was attacked during the Peach Tree War. A group of settlers petitioned this man to end his persecution of Quakers in the (10 pts)",
        "Flushing Remonstrance. This man tore up Richard Nicolls’ surrender offer but later capitulated after hearing advice from his citizens. For ten points, name this director-general of New Netherland, who lost his colony to the Duke of York in 1664."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peter Stuyvesant",
        "“Pieter”",
        "“Petrus” for Peter"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his essay Beating the Averages, Paul Graham argues that this programming language is the reason his startup Viaweb was successful. John McCarthy designed this language, which quickly gained popularity in the AI community. Implementations of this language include (20 pts)",
        "Clojure, Scheme, and its “Common” variant. Emacs uses this programming language for scripting, and the syntax for this language is all (10 pts)",
        "S-expressions. For ten points, name this second oldest high-level programming language after Fortran, known for using lots of parentheses."
      ],
      "answer": "Lisp"
    }
  ]
}